<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The present state of New-England with respect to the Indian War wherein is an account of the true reason thereof (as far as can be judged by men) : together with most of the remarkable passages that have happened from the 20th of June till the 10th of November, 1675 / faithfully composed by a merchant of Boston and communicated to his friend in London.</title>
            <author>N. S.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58611</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S120C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R33574</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13523629</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13523629</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99949</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58611)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99949)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1556:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The present state of New-England with respect to the Indian War wherein is an account of the true reason thereof (as far as can be judged by men) : together with most of the remarkable passages that have happened from the 20th of June till the 10th of November, 1675 / faithfully composed by a merchant of Boston and communicated to his friend in London.</title>
                  <author>N. S.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>81 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Dorman Newman ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1676.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to N.S. by Wing and NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Licensed Decemb. 13, 1675. Roger L'Estrange.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>King Philip's War, 1675-1676.</term>
               <term>New England --  History --  Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99949:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99949:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE PRESENT STATE OF New-England, With Reſpect to the INDIAN WAR.</p>
            <p>Wherein is an Account of the true Reaſon thereof, (as far as can be Judged by Men.)</p>
            <p>Together with moſt of the Remarkable Paſſages that have hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened from the 20th of <hi>June,</hi> till the 10th of <hi>November,</hi> 1675.</p>
            <p>Faithfully Compoſed by a Merchant of <hi>Boſton,</hi> and Communicated to his Friend in <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Licenſed <hi>Decemb.</hi> 13. 1675. <hi>Roger L'Eſtrange.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               <head>C R</head>
               <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
               <q>DIEV ET MON DROIT</q>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed for <hi>Dorman Newman,</hi> at the Kings-Arms in the <hi>Poultry,</hi> and at the Ship and Anchor at the <hi>Bridg</hi>-foot on <hi>Southwark</hi> ſide. 1676.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:99949:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:99949:2"/>
            <head>The Preſent State of <hi>New-England,</hi> with reſpect to the <hi>Indian</hi> War.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here being many and various Reports concerning the Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the preſent War amongſt us, it may not be amiſs in the Firſt place, to give you a true Account of the Reaſons thereof; which probably may add ſomething to the Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of our Chriſtian Friends in <hi>Old England,</hi> which is thus:</p>
            <p>About five or ſix Years ſince, there was brought up (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt others) an <hi>Indian</hi> in the Colledg at <hi>Cambridg,</hi> named <hi>Soſoman,</hi> who after ſome time he had ſpent in Preaching the Goſpel to <hi>Unkus,</hi> a Sagamore Chriſtian in his Territories, was by the Authority of <hi>New-Plimouth,</hi> ſent to Preach in like manner to King <hi>Philip,</hi> and his <hi>Indians:</hi> But King <hi>Philip</hi> (Heathen-like) inſtead of receiving the Goſpel, would imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately have killed this <hi>Soſomon,</hi> but by the perſwaſion of ſome about him, did not do it, but ſent him by the hands of three of his Men to Priſon; who as he was going to Priſon, Exhorted and Taught them in the Chriſtian Religion; they not liking his Diſcourſe, immediately Murthered him after a moſt Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous manner: They returning to King <hi>Philip,</hi> acquainted him what they had done. About two or three Months after, this Murther being Diſcovered to the Authority of <hi>New-Plimouth, Joſiah Winſlow</hi> being then Governour of that Colony, care was taken to find out the Murtherers; who upon ſearch were found and apprehended, and after a fair Trial were all Hanged.</p>
            <p>This ſo Exaſperated King <hi>Philip,</hi> that from that day after, he ſtudied to be Revenged on the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> judging that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Authority have nothing to do to Hang any of his <hi>Indians</hi> for killing another.</p>
            <p>In order thereunto, his firſt Errand is to a <hi>Squaw Sachem</hi> (i. e. a Woman Prince, or Queen) who is Widow of a Brother to King <hi>Philip,</hi> deceaſed, he promiſing her great rewards if ſhe would joyn with him in this Conſpiracy, (for ſhe is as Potent a Prince as any round about her, and hath as much Corn, Land, and Men, at her Command) ſhe willingly conſented, and was much more forward in the Deſign, and had greater Succeſs than King <hi>Philip</hi> himſelf.</p>
            <p>The place where this King <hi>Philip</hi> doth dwell, is on a parcel of Land, called in <hi>Engliſh, Mount-Hope,</hi> about twelve Miles long, and judged to be the beſt Land in <hi>New England:</hi> And it was about thirty five Miles off of this Place to the Northward, that the firſt <hi>Engliſh</hi> that ever came there, Landed; and by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees built Houſes, and called the name of the place <hi>New-Plimouth,</hi> (becauſe <hi>Plimouth</hi> in <hi>Old England</hi> was the laſt place they were at there). The <hi>Engliſh</hi> took not a Foot of Land from the <hi>Indians,</hi> but Bought all, and although they bought for an inconſiderable Value, yet they did Buy it. And it may be judged that now King <hi>Philip</hi> repents himſelf, ſeeing what Product the <hi>Engliſh</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:99949:3"/>have made of a Wilderneſs, through their Labour, and the Bleſſing of God thereon: All the Land of the Colony of <hi>New-Plimouth,</hi> was at firſt Bought of this King <hi>Philip</hi>'s Grand father, <hi>Maſſaſoit</hi> by Name, except ſome few parcels he hath Sold to ſome of the Inhabitants of <hi>Swanzy,</hi> not far from <hi>Mount Hope.</hi> Thereupon about five Years ſince, took an occaſion to Quarrel with the Town, partly becauſe he was vexed he had Sold his Land, and partly becauſe his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther died five or ſix Years before, and he thought the <hi>Engliſh</hi> had Poyſoned him, and thereupon he troubled them, but killed none; but the Governour by timely preparation hindred them of doing any hurt.</p>
            <p>Thus after King <hi>Philip</hi> had ſecured his Intereſt in <hi>Squaw Sachem,</hi> (whom he perſwaded that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> had Poyſoned her Husband, and thereupon ſhe was the more willing to joyn with him) he privately ſent Meſſengers to moſt of the <hi>Indian Sagamores</hi> and <hi>Sachems</hi> round about him, telling them that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> had a Deſign to cut off all the <hi>Indians</hi> round about them, and that if they did not Joyn together, they ſhould loſe their Lives and Lands; whereupon ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Sachems</hi> became his Confederates. And having now five Years time, had opportunity enough to furniſh themſelves with Ammunition and Arms, which they did plentifully at <hi>Canada,</hi> amongſt the <hi>French;</hi> and it is judged that ſome <hi>Engliſh</hi> have alſo Sold them ſome Arms through Ignorance of their Deſign. In the mean time King <hi>Philip</hi> Muſtered up about Five Hundred of his Men, and Arms them compleat; and had gotten about Eight or Nine Hundred of his Neighbouring <hi>Indians,</hi> and likewiſe Arms them compleat; (<hi>i. e.</hi> Guns, Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and Bullets,) but how many he hath engaged to be of his Party, is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to any among us. The laſt Spring ſeveral <hi>Indians</hi> were ſeen in ſmall Parties, about <hi>Rehoboth</hi> and <hi>Swanſey,</hi> which not a little affrighted the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants. Who demanding the Reaſon of them, wherefore it was ſo? Anſwer was made, That they were only on their own Defence, for they underſtood that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> intended to Cut them off. About the <hi>20th</hi> of <hi>June</hi> laſt, Seven or Eight of King <hi>Philip</hi>'s Men came to <hi>Swanſey</hi> on the Lords Day, and would Grind a Hatchet at an Inhabitants Houſe there; the Maſter told them, it was the Sabbath Day, and their God would be very angry if he ſhould let them do it. They returned this anſwer, They knew not who his God was, and that they would do it for all him, or his God either: From thence they went to another Houſe and took away ſome Victuals, but hurt no Man. Immediately they met a Man travelling on the Road, kept him in Cuſtody a ſhort time, then diſmiſt him quietly; giving him this Caution, that he ſhould not Work on his God's Day, and that he ſhould tell no Lies.</p>
            <p>Theſe things happening, with many others of the like Nature, gave the <hi>Rehoboth</hi> and <hi>Swanſey</hi> Men great cauſe of Jealouſies; which occaſioned them to ſend to <hi>Plimouth,</hi> and to the <hi>Bay</hi> (i. e. <hi>Boston</hi>) for ſome Aſſiſtance, in caſe they ſhould need it. But before any came to them, they of both Towns were gathered together into three Houſes, Men, Women, and Children, and there had all Proviſions in common, ſo that they who had nothing wanted not.</p>
            <p>Immediately after, notice came hereof to the Governour of the <hi>Meſſachuſets</hi> Colony (<hi>Boston</hi> being Metropolis, and the Honourable <hi>John Leveret</hi> Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour thereof) Drums beat up for Volunteers, and in three Hours time were Muſtered up about an Hundred and ten men, Captain <hi>Samuel Moſely</hi> being then Commander. This Captain <hi>Moſely</hi> hath been an old Privateer at <hi>Jamaica,</hi> an excellent Souldier, and of an undaunted Spirit, one whoſe Memory will be
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:99949:3"/>Honourable in <hi>New-England,</hi> for his many eminent Services he hath done the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick. There were alſo among theſe men about Ten or Twelve Privateers, that had been there ſometime before: they carried with them ſeveral dogs, that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſerviceable to them, in finding out the Enemy in thir <hi>Swmps;</hi> one whereof, would for ſeveral days together, go out and bring to them ſix, eight, or ten young Pigs of King <hi>Philips</hi> Herds. There went out alſo amongſt theſe Men, one <hi>Cornellis</hi> a <hi>Dutchman,</hi> who had lately been Condemned to die for Piracy, but afterwards received a Pardon, he willing to ſhew his Gratitude therefore, went out and did ſeveral good Services abroad againſt the Enemy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Plimouth</hi> alſo ſent out ſeveral Men at the ſame time, both Horſe and Foot: Alſo moſt Towns in all the United Colonies thereabout ſent out ſome more, ſome leſs, as they were in Number. By this time the <hi>Indians</hi> have killed ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of our Men, but the firſt that was killed was <hi>June</hi> 23, a Man at <hi>Swanſey:</hi> that adventuring with his Wife and Son (about twenty Years old) to go to his Houſe to fetch them corn, and ſuch like things: He having juſt before ſent his Wife and Son away, as he was going out of the Houſe, was ſet on and ſhot by <hi>Indians;</hi> his Wife being not far off, heard the Guns go off, went back: They took her, firſt defiled her, then skinned her Head, as alſo the Son, and diſmiſt them both, who immediately died. They alſo the next day killed ſix or ſeven Men at <hi>Swanſey,</hi> and two more at one of the Garriſons; and as two Men that went out of one of the Garriſons to draw a Bucket of Water, were ſhot and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away, and afterwards found with their Fingers and Feet cut off, and the skin of their Heads flayed off.</p>
            <p>About fourteen days after that, they ſent for more help; whereupon the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of <hi>Boſton,</hi> made Captain <hi>Thomas Savage</hi> the Major General in that Expedition, who with ſixty Horſe, and as many Foot, went out of <hi>Boſton,</hi> having preſt Horſes for the Footmen, and ſix Carts to carry Proviſons with them: Whereof Mr. <hi>John Morſe</hi> was Commiſſary General abroad, and Mr. <hi>Nathaniel Williams</hi> Commiſſary at home. They Travelled day and night till they came to their Garriſons, and within three days after, marched Horſe and Foot (leaving Guards in the Garriſons) towards <hi>Mount Hope,</hi> where King <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> and his Wife was; they came on him at unawares, ſo that <hi>Philip</hi> was forced to riſe from Dinner, and he and all with him fled out of that Land, called <hi>Mount Hope,</hi> up further into the Countrey; they purſued them as far as they could go for <hi>Swamps,</hi> and killed fifteen or ſixteen in that Expedition, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned, and took what he had that was worth taking, and ſpoiled the reſt, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king all his Cattel and Hogs they could find, and alſo took Poſſeſſion of <hi>Mount Hope,</hi> which had then a thouſand Acres under Corn, which is ſince cut down by the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and diſpoſed of according to their Diſcretion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cornellis</hi> was in this Exploit, and purſued <hi>Philip</hi> ſo hard, that he got his Cap off his Head, and now weareth it.</p>
            <p>About three days after, the general (finding <hi>Cornellis</hi> to be a Stout Man, and willing to venture his Life in the Cauſe of the <hi>Engliſh</hi>) ſent him with twelve Men under his Command to Scout about, with Orders to return in three Hours on pain of Death; in his way he met ſixty <hi>Indians</hi> that were halling their <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nooes</hi> a-ſhore, he ſet on them, killing thirteen, and took eight alive, purſes the reſt as for as he could go for the <hi>Swamps;</hi> then he returned and Burnt all thoſe <hi>Cannooes,</hi> about forty in number: By this time <hi>Cornellis</hi> and his twelve
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:99949:4"/>Men (all being perſerved) returned to the Camp, but they were eight Hours abſent: Whereupon a Council of War was called, who paſt the Sentence of Death on him, for exceeding the Order given him. Immediately was alſo Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned, and received thanks for his good Service done in that Expedition; and was in a ſhort time ſent out on the like Deſign, and brought Home with him twelve <hi>Indians</hi> alive, and two <hi>Indians</hi> Heads (<hi>i. e.</hi> the Skin with the Hair on it.)</p>
            <p>About the <hi>25th</hi> of <hi>July,</hi> the General returned with twelve Men to guard his Perſon,</p>
            <p>Captain <hi>Moſely</hi> being there, and plying about, found Eighty <hi>Indians</hi> who ſurrendred themſelves, and were ſecured in a Houſe, provided for them near <hi>Plimouth:</hi> Thereupon came to <hi>Boſton,</hi> to know the pleaſure of the Authority about them, and in a days time returned with this Order; he ſhould kill none that he took alive, but ſecure them in order to a Tranſportation: Wherefore afterwards there were Shipt on board Captain <hi>Sprague</hi> an Hundred ſeventy eight <hi>Indians,</hi> on the <hi>28th</hi> of <hi>September,</hi> bound for <hi>Cales.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this time, the <hi>Indians</hi> continued daily to commit many Acts of Hoſtility on the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> they Burnt Twenty three Houſes at <hi>Swanſey,</hi> and killed many People there, and took much Cattle, as alſo Burnt the Hay and Corn in great quantities. They Burnt near thirty Houſes in <hi>Dartmouth,</hi> (a place in <hi>New-Plimouth</hi> Colony) killing many People after a moſt Barbarous manner; as skin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them all over alive, ſome only their Heads, cutting off their Hands and Feet; but any Woman they take alive, they Defile, afterwards put her to Death by ſome of thoſe or the like ways. They have Burnt moſt of the Houſes in <hi>Rehoboth, Taunton,</hi> and <hi>Swanſey;</hi> a Party of <hi>Indians</hi> came to <hi>Mendham,</hi> which is Thirty two Miles from <hi>Boſton,</hi> and there killed five or ſix Perſons, who being purſued, two were killed, the reſt fled.</p>
            <p>Some part of our Forces afterwards ſet on about Five hundred <hi>Indians,</hi> not far from <hi>Pocaſſit,</hi> purſuing them into a larg <hi>Swamp,</hi> not far from thence; how many they killed is not known, in regard the <hi>Indians</hi> adventured back and took their dead Men away with them: (as they commonly do if they can poſſibly) But in this Fight were killed King <hi>Philips</hi> Brother, his Privy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor, (being one formerly Educated at <hi>Cambridg</hi>) and one of his chief Captains; the Heads of which three were afterwards brought to <hi>Boſton.</hi> There were killed in this purſuit ſix <hi>Engliſhmen,</hi> and nine or ten wounded.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Pocaſſit Swamp,</hi> is judged about ſeven or eight Miles long, and ſo full of Buſhes and Trees, that a parcel of <hi>Indians</hi> may be within the length of a Pike of a Man, and he cannot diſcover them; and beſides, this as well as all other <hi>Swamps,</hi> is ſo ſoft Ground, that an <hi>Engliſhman</hi> can neither go nor ſtand thereon, and yet theſe bloody Savages will run a long over it, holding their Guns croſs their arms (and if occaſion be) diſcharge in that poſture.</p>
            <p>On the Lords Day, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>July,</hi> an <hi>Indian</hi> came to <hi>Dorcheſter,</hi> (within half a Mile of Mother <hi>Georges</hi> Houſe) to the Houſe of Mr. <hi>Minor,</hi> in Sermon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, and there were then at Home the Maid ſervant and two young Children, ſhe keeping the Door ſhut for ſafety; the <hi>Indian</hi> when he ſaw he could not come in at the Door, went about to come in at the Window, ſhe perceiving his reſolution, took two braſs kettles, under which ſhe put the two children, ſhe ran up Stairs and charged a Musket and fired at the <hi>Indian,</hi> (he having fired
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:99949:4"/>at her once or twice and miſt her, but ſtruck the top of one Kettle, under which a Child was) and ſhot him into his ſhoulder; then he let his Gun fall, and was juſt coming in at the Window, ſhe made haſte and got a Fire ſhovel full of live Coles and applied them to his Face, which forced him to flie and eſcaped: But one was found dead within five Miles of that place afterwards, and was judged to be this by his ſcalded Face.</p>
            <p>Theſe Tranſactions may be computed to end with <hi>July.</hi> Before any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther progreſs be made in this Relation, it may not be amiſs to give you ſome Account of what concerns our Neighbour <hi>Indians</hi> at Peace with us.</p>
            <p>There are two Potent <hi>Sagamores,</hi> that are in Amity with us: The one is <hi>Ninnicroft,</hi> his Territories border on <hi>Connecticot</hi> Colony; the other is <hi>Unkus,</hi> the only Chriſtian <hi>Sagamore</hi> among them.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Unkus,</hi> and all his Subjects profeſſing Chriſtanity, are called <hi>Praying Indians.</hi> In the firſt week in <hi>Auguſt,</hi> the Authority of <hi>Boſton</hi> ſent an Expreſs to him, to require him to come in and Surrender himſelf, man, and Armes, to the <hi>Engliſh:</hi> whereupon, he ſent along with the Meſſenger his three Sons, and about Sixty of his Men, with his Arms, to be thus diſpoſed of, <hi>viz.</hi> His two youngeſt Sons, (about thirty Years old) to remain as Hoſtages (as now they do at <hi>Cambridg</hi>) and his Eldeſt Son to go Captain of the Men as Aſſiſtants to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> againſt the Heathens, which accordingly they did. And the <hi>Engliſh</hi> not thinking themſelves yet ſecure enough, becauſe they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not know a Heathen from a Chriſtian by his Viſage, nor Apparel: The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of <hi>Boſton,</hi> at a Council held there the <hi>30th</hi> of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> Publiſhed this following Order.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>AT A COUNCIL Held in BOSTON, <hi>August</hi> 30. 1675.</head>
                  <p>THe Council judging it of abſolute neceſſity for the Security of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and the <hi>Indians</hi> that are in Amity with us, that they be Reſtrained their uſual Commerce with the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and Hunting in the Woods, during the time of Hoſtility with thoſe that are our Enemies.</p>
                  <p>Do Order, that all thoſe <hi>Indians</hi> that are deſirous to Approve themſelves faithful to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> be Confined to their ſeveral Plantations under-written, until the Council ſhall take further order; and that they ſo order the ſetting of their Wigwams, that they may ſtand
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:99949:5"/>Compact in ſome one part of their Plantations reſpectively, where it may be beſt for their own Proviſion &amp; Defence. And that none of them do preſume to Travel above one Mile from the Center of ſuch their Dwelling, unleſs in company with ſome <hi>Engliſh,</hi> or in their Service near their Dwellings; and excepting for gathering &amp; fetch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their Corn with one <hi>Engliſhman,</hi> on peril of being taken as our Enemies, or their Abettors: And in caſe that any of them ſhall be taken without the Limits a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boveſaid, except as aboveſaid, and do loſe their Lives, or be otherwiſe damnified, by <hi>Engliſh</hi> or <hi>Indians;</hi> The Council do hereby Declare, that they ſhall account themſelves wholly Innocent, and their Blood or other Damage (by them ſuſtained) will be upon their own Heads.</p>
                  <p>Alſo, it ſhall not be lawful for any <hi>Indians</hi> that are in Amity with us, to entertain any ſtrange <hi>Indians,</hi> or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive any of our Enemies Plunder, but ſhall from time to time make diſcovery thereof to ſome <hi>Engliſh,</hi> that ſhall be Appointed for that end to ſojourn among them, on penalty of being reputed our Enemies, and of being lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be proceeded againſt as ſuch.</p>
                  <p>Alſo, whereas it is the manner of the Heathens that are now in Hoſtility with us, contrary to the Practice of all Civil Nations, to execute their bloody Inſolencies by Stealth, and Sculking in ſmall Parties, declining all open deciſion of their Controverſie, either by Treaty or by the Sword.</p>
                  <p>The Council do therefore Order, that after the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication of the Proviſion aforeſaid, It ſhall be lawful for any Perſon, whether <hi>Engliſh</hi> or <hi>Indian,</hi> that ſhall find any <hi>Indians</hi> Travelling or Sculking in any of our Towns or Woods, contrary to the Limits above-named, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand them under their Guard, and Examination, or to Kill and deſtroy them as they beſt may or can. The Council hereby declaring, That it will be moſt accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to them that none be Killed or Wounded, that are willing to ſurrender themſelves into Cuſtody.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Places of the <hi>Indians</hi> Reſidencies are, <hi>Natick, Punquapaog, Naſhoba, Wameſit,</hi> and <hi>Haſſanemeſit:</hi> And if there be any that belong to any other Plantations, they are to Repair to ſome one of theſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>By the Council. <hi>Edward Rawſon,</hi> Secr.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:99949:5"/>
            <p>Which company of Praying <hi>Indians</hi> marched out of Town (having Saluted the Governour with three Volleys) and were appointed to march in the Front, which they did, and met with ſeveral Skirmiſhes, in which they Killed ſome, and about forty-five more Surrendred themſelves; which were ſhipt off a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe Captain <hi>Sprague</hi> carried away.</p>
            <p>Concerning the <hi>Narraganſets, Ninnicroft</hi> is their <hi>Sagamore;</hi> his Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Father, and Father, always kept Truce with the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> but he now gives ſufficient cauſe to think otherwiſe of him.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Squaw Sachem,</hi> having ran very far in her Engagements with King <hi>Philip,</hi> and fearing leſt ſhe ſhould be taken, ſhe committed her Perſon to the poſſeſſion of this <hi>Ninnicroft,</hi> judging her ſelf ſafe by virtue of his Protection; where ſhe hath continued ever ſince <hi>July</hi> laſt. Whereupon a certain number of Men were ſent by the Authority of <hi>Connecticot</hi> Colony (<hi>John Wenthrop</hi> Governour) to the <hi>Narraganſets,</hi> to require them to deliver the Queen, and withal to Ratifie that long Peace they had maintained with the <hi>Engliſh:</hi> Whereupon the <hi>Narraganſets</hi> concluded a Peace with them, and ſent a Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Men to <hi>Connecticot,</hi> for the aſſiſtance of the <hi>Engliſh.</hi> The <hi>Engliſh</hi> made this Agreement with them, That for every <hi>Indians</hi> Head-skin they brought, they ſhould have a Coat, (<hi>i. e.</hi> two Yards of Trucking Cloth, worth five Shillings <hi>per</hi> Yard here) and for every one they bring alive, two Coats; for King <hi>Philips</hi> Head, Twenty Coats; and if taken alive, Forty Coats: Theſe went out, and returned in fourteen days time, bringing with them about Eighteen Heads in all.</p>
            <p>Several other <hi>Sachems</hi> of the Countries, called in <hi>Indian, Nipmog,</hi> came to an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Town called <hi>Brookfield,</hi> (but in <hi>Indian, Quawbawg,</hi> during the time our Garriſon was there) and told them they were Praying <hi>Indians,</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> Chriſtians) and that they would be quiet, and do no harm to the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh;</hi> but withal, told them, that for their own ſafety they could not deliver up their Arms: But the Inhabitants of <hi>Brookfield</hi> thought they would be Faithful, in regard they were Praying <hi>Indians,</hi> took their words and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt them.</p>
            <p>The Authority of <hi>Boſton,</hi> with the Advice of the Governour of <hi>Connecticot,</hi> as alſo of <hi>Plimouth</hi> Colonies, then ſitting in Councel for ſeveral days together at <hi>Boſton,</hi> For their better ſatisfaction, ſent a Party of thirty Horſe under the Command of Captain <hi>Hutchinſon,</hi> and Captain <hi>Wheeler;</hi> when they were come to <hi>Quawbawg,</hi> they ſent a Party of Horſe to the <hi>Nipmoog Sachems</hi> to Treat with them. (For you muſt underſtand that Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Hutchinſon</hi> had a very conſiderable Farm thereabouts, and had occaſion to imploy ſeveral of thoſe <hi>Sachems</hi> Men, in Tilling and Plowing his Ground, and thereby he was known by Face to many of them.) The <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chems</hi> ſent this word, they would ſpeak with none but Captain <hi>Hutchinſon</hi> himſelf; whereupon Capt. <hi>Hutchinſon</hi> and Capt. <hi>Wheeler,</hi> ſent them word they would come to them themſelves: Accordingly the <hi>Indians</hi> appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the meeting at ſuch a Tree, and at ſuch a time. The time being come, Captain <hi>Hutchiſon,</hi> Captain <hi>Wheeler,</hi> and his Company, (with ſome of the Inhabitants of <hi>Brookfield,</hi> who thought them to be very Honeſt, therefore took no Arms with them) went to the place, but the <hi>Nipmoog Indians</hi> were not there. Whereupon the Guide that conducted them through the Woods, brought them to a <hi>Swamp,</hi> not far off the appointed place; out of which
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:99949:6"/>theſe <hi>Indians</hi> ran all at once and Killed ſixteen Men, and Wounded ſeveral others, of which Wounds three Weeks after, Captain <hi>Hutchiſon</hi> died, when his Wife and Son were within twelve Miles of him in their Journey to ſee him; whoſe Death is the more lamented, in that his Mother, and ſeveral others of his Relations, died by the hands of the <hi>Indians,</hi> now near forty Years ſince.</p>
            <p>The reſt that eſcaped, made what haſte they could to the Town of <hi>Brook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field,</hi> they made choice of the ſtrongeſt Houſe there, reſolved to make a Garriſon of it; in order thereunto, as ſoon as they could, got all the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple (about Eighty in number) into this Houſe. The <hi>Indians</hi> purſued them cloſe, and in four Hours time had Burnt twenty and odd Houſes in <hi>Brookfield,</hi> and abode thereabout three or four days, ſhooting day and night, with moſt dreadful Screechings and Yellings, which ſignified their Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph. They in this time endeavoured to ſet the Garriſon on fire divers times, but by the Providence of God were prevented; once by a ſhowre of Rain, another time by their Diligence within. One from within ſtept out to drink ſome Water and was killed, and one more killed within. The Bruits had contrived an Engin with many Wheels, to fire the Garriſon ten or twelve Rod off, and had loaded it with combuſtibles therefore, (and news was brought to <hi>Boſton</hi> that they were all Burnt, but it was not ſo) and had aſſuredly done it, had not Major <hi>Willard</hi> come to their Relief with a flying Army of ſixty Horſe, at nine or ten a Clock at Night: They forced their way through the Body of the <hi>Indians,</hi> and Fired a pace on them, and in two Hours time wholly Routed the <hi>Indians</hi> thence, killing ſeveral. Thus deliverance was wrought by a mighty Hand for them, when they had no outward reaſon to expect any.</p>
            <p>During the time theſe People kept themſelves in that Houſe, two Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men were ſafely delivered of two Sons apiece, who in a Months time brought them all themſelves on foot to <hi>Boſton,</hi> where they were plentifully releived out of the Church-Stock there.</p>
            <p>There are alſo another ſort of <hi>Indians,</hi> (beſt know to the Commonalty of <hi>Boſton</hi>) by the name of Mr. <hi>Elliots Indians,</hi> or Captain <hi>Guggins Indians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Mr. <hi>Elliot,</hi> you muſt underſtand, is the Man that hath by his own great Labour and Study, invented the way of Printing the <hi>Indian</hi> Language, and hath alſo perfectly Tranſlated the whole Bible, with the Singing Pſalms in Meeter; the Aſſemblies Catechiſm; the Practiſe of Piety, into the <hi>Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Language; as alſo Written ſeveral Books, very profitable for underſtanding the Grounds of Chriſtian Religion: For which Pains and Labour, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves Honour from all ſuch who are Well-wiſhers to things of the like Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, whoſe Name will never Die in <hi>New-England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A <hi>Specimen</hi> of his Tranſlation of the Bible into the <hi>Indian</hi> Language is as followeth.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:99949:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <head>Iſaiah, Chap. <hi>23.</hi> Ver. <hi>1, 2, 3.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>OOWeanun Tyre. OOnook kenaau Tarſhiſhe kuhtoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nogquog, newutche mahchimoo, newaj matta wetuwoniuneog, wanne petut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teaun: wutch Chittimme ohkert nag wehteauwahuoneau.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>THe burden of Tyre. Howl ye ſhips of Tarſhiſh, for it is laid waste, ſo that there is no houſe, no entring in: From the land of Chittim it is revealed to them.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2. Chequnappek wadohkeogiſh mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nohhanehtu, ken, Zidone anaqiſhae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuog neg quoſhkodteacheg keitoh, kenum wamechumuhkonukquog.</cell>
                     <cell>2. <hi>Be ſtill ye Inhabitants of the Iſle, thou whom the Merchants of Zidon that paſs over the Sea, have repleniſhed.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3. Kah naſhpe miſhe nippeaſh, wuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kanuem Sihor, ſepue kepenumoonk ne wutte ſhegenoom, kah noh wutohtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inne ahhut kodtauwompatimuk.</cell>
                     <cell>3. <hi>And by great waters the ſeed of Sihor, the harveſt of the River is her revenue, and ſhe is a Mart of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>This Captain <hi>Guggins,</hi> is a Captain and Juſtice of Peace at <hi>Cambridg:</hi> He receives Thirty Pound <hi>per annum</hi> from the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> to ſit as Judg among the <hi>Indians,</hi> to Judg any difference (not Capital) among themſelves, or between them and the <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of theſe <hi>Indians</hi> thus diſtingiſhed, it may not be amiſs to give a brief Account, in its proper place.</p>
            <p>Now it falls in Courſe, to think on what is done in the Field on both Sides.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Thurſday</hi> the <hi>5th</hi> of <hi>August,</hi> being Lecture-day at <hi>Boston,</hi> was ordered by the Old Church (of which the Governour is a Member) to be obſerved as a Faſt by that Church, which accordingly was done: And at the Contribution was then Collected Sixty Nine Pound, which was for the diſtreſſed Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies Relief. And on that very day was Captain <hi>Hutchiſons</hi> Company ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated: Which thing was taken eſpecial Notice of, by all thoſe who deſire to ſee the Hand of God in ſuch ſad Providences, which did occaſion ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Faſt to be kept, by Mr. <hi>Mathers</hi> Church, at the North Meeting-houſe the <hi>Wedneſday</hi> following.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Wedneſday,</hi> the <hi>12th</hi> of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> was appointed a Faſt for Mr. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's</hi> Church, which was duly obſerved; that day being a Court day for the Council, no Magiſtrate was there, yet notwithſtanding there was ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered at the Contribution ſixty eight Pound.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Mather</hi> in his Sermon, took occaſion too in ſpeaking of the Benefit of Communion with God, to tell us that there are in this Colony ſeventy nine gathered Churches, and that to this day the <hi>Indians</hi> had not done any Dammage to any thing that belonged to any of the Places where theſe Churches were.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Auguſt</hi> coming on, we have now from all Parts raiſed more Men, ſo that there are now in the Field in ſeveral places, ſix hundred Horſe and Foot: Moſt of the Army were not far from the <hi>Swamp</hi> wherein King <hi>Philip</hi> with all his People were; they reſolved to compaſs it, which they did once: And in their ſecond Encounter, forced King <hi>Philip</hi> with all his Retinue out of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:99949:7"/>the <hi>Samp,</hi> and purſued them; in their purſuit they killed his Lievetenant-General, with about twenty (that they ſaw of his Men, and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> had not the loſs of one Man, but two wounded. We having all this while a Party of <hi>Unkus</hi>'s <hi>Indians</hi> in the Field on our ſide.</p>
            <p>About the <hi>15th</hi> of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> Captain <hi>Moſely</hi> with ſixty Men, Met with a company, judged about three hundred <hi>Indians,</hi> in a plain place where few Trees were, and on both ſides preparations were making for a Battle; all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ready on both ſides to fight, Captain <hi>Moſeley</hi> plucked off his Periwig, and put it into his Breeches, becauſe it ſhould not hinder him in fighting. As ſoon as the <hi>Indians</hi> ſaw that, they fell a Howling and Yelling moſt hide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, and ſaid, <hi>Umh, umh me no ſtawmerre fight Engis mon, Engis mon get two hed, Engis mon got two hed; if me cut off un hed, he got noder, a put on beder as dis;</hi> with ſuch like words in broken <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and away they all fled and could not be overtaken, nor ſeen any more afterwards. About a Week after this, Capt. <hi>Moſeley</hi> took two <hi>Indians,</hi> the Father and his Son, and willing to Examin them both apart, proceeded thus: Took the old Man and bound him to a Tree, after he was ſo bound, he ſent away the Son by a File of Men out of ſight; the old Man there confeſt he was a <hi>Praying Indian,</hi> and that he was only hunting for Deer thereabouts; but ſaid, that his Son was one of thoſe Men that wounded Captain <hi>Hutchiſon:</hi> So then, after they had pump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him as much as they could, they fired a Gun with no Bullet in it over his Head, untied him, and ſent him another way with a File out of ſight; then brought they his Son, bound him in like manner, they telling him that they had ſhot his Father, and would ſhoot him alſo, if he would not confeſs what he was, and what he knew: He fairly told them, that he was a <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Indian,</hi> but his Father made him go with him to the <hi>Nipmoog Indians,</hi> and that there they ſhot three or four times apiece; whereupon they then brought the old Man and tyed him to his Son, and Examined them together; at length they confeſt they were both among the <hi>Nipmoogs,</hi> and that the Son did wound Captain <hi>Hutchiſon;</hi> after their Examination, they were both ſhot to Death.</p>
            <p>In this ſame Week, King <hi>Philips</hi> Men had taken a young Lad alive about fourteen Years old, and bound him to a Tree two nights and two days, intending to be Merry with him the Next day, and that they would Roaſt him alive to make ſport with him; but God over-night, touched the heart of one <hi>Indian,</hi> ſo that he came and looſed him, and bid him <hi>run Grande</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> run Apace) and by that means he eſcaped.</p>
            <p>Towards the latter end of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> Captain <hi>Moſeley</hi> took eight <hi>Indians</hi> alive, and ſent them Priſoners to <hi>Boſton,</hi> who were put in Priſon there; theſe were of the Number of Mr. <hi>Eliot's Indians;</hi> (as alſo many of thoſe <hi>Indians</hi> that were Shipt off by Captain <hi>Sprague,</hi> for the <hi>Straits</hi> and <hi>Cales</hi>) theſe Men were at ſeveral times tryed for their Lives, and condemned to Die: Mean time Mr. <hi>Eliot,</hi> and Captain <hi>Guggins,</hi> pleaded ſo very hard for the <hi>Indians,</hi> that the whole Council knew not what to do about them. They hearkned to Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi> for his Gravity, Age, and Wiſdom, and alſo for that he hath been the chief Inſtrument that the Lord hath made uſe of, in Propagating the Goſpel among the Heathen; And was their Teacher, till ſuch time that ſome <hi>Indians</hi> were brought upon in the Univerſity to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply his place. But for Captain <hi>Guggins,</hi> why ſuch a wiſe Council as
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:99949:7"/>they, ſhould be ſo over-born by him, cannot be judged otherwiſe then becauſe of his daily troubling them with his Impertinences and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudinous Speeches, in ſo much that it was told him on the Bench, by<note n="†" place="margin">Cap. <hi>Oliver.</hi>
               </note> a very worthy Perſon there preſent, that he ought rather to be Confined among his <hi>Indians,</hi> than to ſit on the Bench; his taking the <hi>Indians</hi> part ſo much hath made him a By-word both among Men and Boys. But ſo it was, that by one, and two at a time, moſt of theſe eight <hi>Indians,</hi> (and four more ſent afterwards on the ſame account) were let looſe by night, which ſo Exaſperated the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monalty, that about the <hi>10th</hi> of <hi>September,</hi> at nine a Clock at night, there gathered together about forty Men (ſome of note) and came to the Houſe of Captain <hi>James Oliver;</hi> two or three of them went into his En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try to deſire to ſpeak with him, which was to deſire him to be their Leader, and they ſhould joyn together and go break open the Priſon, and take one <hi>Indian</hi> out thence and Hang him: Captain <hi>Oliver</hi> hearing their requeſt, took his Cane and cudgelled them ſtoutly, and ſo for that time diſmiſt the Company; which had he but in the leaſt countenanced, it might have been accompanied with ill Events in the end. Immediately Captain <hi>Oliver</hi> went and acquainted Mr. <hi>Ting</hi> his Neighbour, (a Juſtice of Peace) and they both went the next Morning and acquainted the Goverour, who thank'd Captain <hi>Oliver</hi> for what he had done laſt night, but this reſted not here: For the Commonalty were ſo enraged againſt Mr. <hi>Elliot,</hi> and Captain <hi>Guggins</hi> eſpecially, that Captain <hi>Guggins</hi> ſaid on the Bench, that he was afraid to go along the ſtreets; the anſwer was made, you may thank your ſelf; however an Order was iſſued out for the Execution of that one (notorious above the reſt) <hi>Indian,</hi> and accordingly he was led by a Rope about his Neck to the Gallows; when he came there, the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioners (for there were many) flung one end over the Poſt, and ſo hoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him up like a Dog, three or four times, he being yet half alive, and half dead; then came an <hi>Indian,</hi> a Friend of his, and with his Knife made a hole in his Breaſt to his Heart, and ſucked out his Heart-blood: Being asked his reaſon therefore, his anſwer, <hi>Umh, umh nu,</hi> Me ſtronger as I was before, me be ſo ſtrong as me and he too, he be ver ſtrong Man fore he die.</p>
            <p>Thus with the Dog-like-death (good enough) of one poor Heathen, was the Peoples Rage laid in ſome meaſure, but in a ſhort time it began to work (not without Cauſe enough). About the beginning of <hi>Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> Captain <hi>Hinksman</hi> was ſent out Commander of one hundred Men, and were to meet together at <hi>Roxbury</hi> Meeting-Houſe-yard, when they were there, ready to March, they all unanimouſly reſolved not to go with him, but if Captain <hi>Oliver</hi> would go, they would go gladly; whereupon the Council ſent for him Home, and ſent Captain <hi>Lake</hi> in his room.</p>
            <p>On <hi>wedneſday, Auguſt</hi> 25. was obſerved a Faſt at <hi>Charles</hi>-Town, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſeveral of <hi>Boſton</hi> went, there was gathered that day Seventy eight Pound.</p>
            <p>King <hi>Philip</hi> now beinning to want Money (having a Coat made all of <hi>Wampampeag,</hi> (i. e. <hi>Indian</hi> Money) cuts his Coat to pieces, and diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes it plentifully among the <hi>Nipmoog Sachems</hi> and others, as well to the <hi>Eaſtward</hi> as <hi>Southward,</hi> and all round about. This gives occaſion to ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:99949:8"/>that the <hi>Narraganſets</hi> may alſo be Bribed, who are out on our ſide, in that they follow not Orders to purſue King <hi>Philip</hi> effectually. Captain <hi>Lathrop,</hi> and Captain <hi>Beers,</hi> being at <hi>Hadly,</hi> and there hearing of an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian</hi> Caſtle not far thence, they marched with an Hundred and eighty Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers thither, who required the <hi>Indians</hi> to ſurrender their Armes; the <hi>Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> told Captain <hi>Beers,</hi> that they would the next Morning. But the Captains with their Men ſoon made themſelves Maſters thereof, forcing them into a <hi>Swamp,</hi> having killed nine or ten, they Retreated.</p>
            <p>By this time the Town of <hi>Deerfield</hi> begins to be in danger: Whereupon Captain <hi>Beers</hi> with eighty Men went to bring away the People, the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants thereof. The <hi>Indians</hi> having Burnt twenty five Houſes; in their way, they were met with by a parcel of <hi>Indians</hi> of about a Hundred and fifty, which the <hi>Engliſh</hi> got the better of, killing neer Forty <hi>Indians,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving loſt but four or five <hi>Engliſhmen:</hi> But immediately there did appear the greateſt Body that hath at one time been ſeen by the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and fell upon Captain <hi>Beers,</hi> immediately killing him and ſixty five of his Men, and fifteen eſcaped; theſe fifteen ran to Captain <hi>Moſeley,</hi> who then was about nine or ten Miles off, he came with his ſixty Men, and gave the whole Body of the <hi>Indians</hi> Battel (judged about one thouſand two hundred) for three Hours; whereupon after having killed ſeveral of the <hi>Indians,</hi> he was forced to Retreat, and continued Fighting for all the time that he and his Men were Retreating nine Miles; Captain <hi>Moſeley</hi> loſt out of his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany nine, and thirteen wounded. The next day they come up again, the <hi>Indians</hi> were gone, they had ſtript the dead Men of all their Clothes and Arms, and Horſes; amongſt which dead, was one who had life in him, and was found by a Friend <hi>Indian,</hi> he took him up and ſaid, <hi>Umh, umh poo Ingiſmon, mee ſave yow life, mee take yow to Captain Moſee;</hi> he car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries him fifteen Miles the day after to Captain <hi>Moſeley,</hi> and now this Man is well again and in good health.</p>
            <p>Immediately Orders were taken at <hi>Boston</hi> for the ſending out more Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, as many as to make up Captain <hi>Moſeleys</hi> Company an Hundred com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat, were forthwith ſent away: They are fitting out an Hundred more from <hi>Connecticot,</hi> under the Command of Major <hi>Treat,</hi> and Captain <hi>Whiting</hi> the Miniſter of <hi>Hartford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>September</hi> 10, Eight <hi>Indians</hi> came to <hi>Boſton</hi> from <hi>Ninnicroft,</hi> in an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſy, having a Certificate from Captain <hi>Smith</hi> an <hi>Engliſhman,</hi> that hath a large Eſtate thereabouts: They diſpatched their Buſineſs, and had ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Paſs, tied at the end of a Stick, that <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> may ſee it afar off. They were going out of Town a back way, two Men men met them, and ſeized on him that had the Paſs; theſe two Men were Brothers, and this <hi>Indian</hi> had been among King <hi>Philips Indians,</hi> and theſe two Men Swore in Court, that that was the Man that killed their Brother, they knew him; whereupon two days after his Trial and Confeſſion, he was Hanged like the other.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>September</hi> 23. About ten at night we had an Allarm given us, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore eleven we had one Thouſand two Hundred Men in Armes, and diſmiſt by twelve that night: The occaſion was, one of the Watch was Drunk about thirty Miles off at <hi>Mendham,</hi> and he fired a Gun, ſo it came to <hi>Boston;</hi> the next morning he paid ten Shillings, and ſat ſome hours in the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:99949:8"/>Stocks for his being Drunk, and afterwards had twenty Laſhes for giving a falſe Allarm.</p>
            <p>On the <hi>28th</hi> day of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> happened here at eleven a Clock at night, a moſt violent Storm of Wind and Rain, the like was never known before; it blew up many Ships together that they Bulged one another, ſome up to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>words <hi>Cambridg,</hi> ſome to <hi>Muddy-River,</hi> doing much hurt to very many; alſo it broke down many Wharffs, and blew down ſome Houſes thereupon. The <hi>Indians</hi> afterwards reported that they had cauſed it by their <hi>Pawwaw,</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> worſhipping the Devil). They farther ſay, That as many <hi>Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> ſhall Die, as the Trees have by this Wind been blown down in the Woods: But theſe Heatheniſh notions are conſonant to their barbarous Crueltie, and ought to be valued accordingly, by all who own any thing ſuperiour to it or them.</p>
            <p>Several Men, ſome whereof are <hi>Quakers,</hi> will not go out on Command, and for their diſobedience thereunto, are forced to run the Gantelop.</p>
            <p>About the <hi>15th</hi> of <hi>September,</hi> the Authority of <hi>Boston</hi> ſent a Party to <hi>Nin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicroft,</hi> to require him to come to <hi>Boſton,</hi> to treat concerning the delivery <hi>Squaw Sachem:</hi> He ſent word he would come, provided he might be ſafely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned back; Captain <hi>Smith</hi> living near him, offered himſelf, Wife and Children, and Eſtate, as Hoſtages therefore.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ninnicroft</hi> ſeeing this, reſolved to ſend his Eldeſt Son thither (he himſelf being very aged) ſo away they came, bringing Captain <hi>Smith</hi> with them; when they came to <hi>Roxbury,</hi> they ſent word to <hi>Boston</hi> they were come, and deſired to know if they might have admittance into <hi>Boston:</hi> Word was ſent them, that they ſhould be very welcome. In order thereto, Captain <hi>James Oliver,</hi> and Captain <hi>Clark,</hi> were ordered with ſix Files of Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quets a piece to meet on the Neck, to conduct them into Town. The <hi>Indians</hi> meeting theſe Captains, thought that they were all to Die imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately; ſome were for running away, and ſome not, but Captain <hi>Smith</hi> being with them, endeavoured to pacifie them as well as he could. When they met, they opened to the Right and Left, and gave them three Vol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys, and ſo Guarded them to the Governours Houſe. The next Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this <hi>Sagamore</hi> with all his Retinue, went to Captain <hi>Olivers</hi> Houſe, to give him hearty thanks for Yeſterdays kindneſs, in his conducting them ſafe to Town.</p>
            <p>The Council ſat every day during their abode in <hi>Boston,</hi> until they came to an Agreement: The <hi>Narraganſets</hi> by degrees, came to this Agreement, That they were to deliver the <hi>Squaw Sachem</hi> within ſo many days at <hi>Boſton;</hi> and the League of Peace was then by them confirmed, which was much to the general ſatisfaction; but yet many had hard thoughts of them, fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they will at laſt prove Treacherous: They were diſmiſt out of Town in ſafety, according to their deſire.</p>
            <p>The Governour and Council ſeeing, and ſeriouſly conſidering the Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that many had already undergone, and that the Countrey was like to be in, Iſſued out this following Order for a Solemn Faſt all over the Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; which was performed with a very great ſhew of outward Penitence, and (no queſtion) with much inward Affection by very many: The Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour himſelf beginning the duty of the Day, with a moſt heavenly Prayer.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:99949:9"/>
                  <head>AT A COUNCIL Held at BOSTON, <hi>Sept.</hi> 17. 1675.</head>
                  <p>IT pleaſed the HOLY GOD (all whoſe Works are Truth, and his Ways Judgment) for our ſins whereby he hath been provoked, in ſpecial by the under-valuation of our pleaſant things; great un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfulneſſe for, and manifold abuſes of our won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Peace, and the Bleſſings of it in this good Land, which the Lord hath given us; ill entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Miniſtry of the precious Goſpel of Peace: Leaving our firſt-Love, dealing falſly in the Covenant of the Lord our God: The Apoſtacy of many from the Truth unto Hereſies, and pernicious Errours; Great Formality, inordinate Affection, and ſinful Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to this preſent evil vain World: And (beſide ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny horrid and ſcandalous Sins breaking forth among us, for which we have cauſe to be greatly humbled before the Lord) our great unſenſibleneſs of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure of the Lord in ſuffering theſe Abominations to be perpetrated, together with our Carnal Securi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and unquietneſs under the Iudgments of God upon us; our abiding very much unreformed, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all Warnings and Chaſtiſements, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Lord hath been, and is ſtill debating with us; we having greatly incenſed Him to ſtir up many Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries againſt us, not only Abroad, but alſo at our own Doors, (cauſing the Heathen in this Wilderneſs to be as thorns in our ſides, who have formerly been, and might ſtill be, a Wall unto us therein; and others alſo to become a Scourge unto us) the Lord himſelf alſo more immediately Afflicting us by Diſeaſes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſo many Children in ſome of our Towns have died this Summer. His not going forth with our Armies
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:99949:9"/>as in former times, but giving up many of our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren to the Mouth of the devouring Sword, yea, ſhewing himſelf Angry with the Prayers of his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: Threatning us alſo with ſcarcity of Proviſion and other Calamities, eſpecially if this preſent War with the barbarous Heathen ſhould continue: And that the Lord of Hoſts himſelf withdraw not the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion He hath given to the Sword, and other Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to prevail againſt us.</p>
                  <p>The Governour and Council of this Iuriſdiction therefore (being under the Senſe of theſe evils, and alſo of the diſtreſſed State of the reſt of the Colonies confederate with our ſelves, and of the Churches of Chriſt in other parts of the Chriſtian World, in this day of Trouble, Rebukes, and Blaſphemy; and fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſad Iſſue thereof, unleſs the Lord help us with our whole Heart, and not feignedly, to turn unto Himſelf) Do Appoint, and Order the ſeventh day of the next Month, to be a Day of Publick Humiliation, with Faſting and Prayer, throughout this whole Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lony; that we may ſet our ſelves ſincerely to ſeek the Lord, rending our Hearts, and not our Garments before Him, and purſue the ſame with a through Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of what ever hath been, or is an Image of Iealouſie before the Lord, to offend the Eyes of his Glory; if ſo be, the Lord may turn from his fierce Anger, that we periſh not. We do therefore require all the Inhabitants of this Iuriſdiction to forbear Servile Labour upon that Day, and that they apply themſelves reſpectively to obſerve the ſame, as is Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>By the Council. <hi>Edward Rawſon,</hi> Secr.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:99949:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>On the <hi>1ſt</hi> of <hi>October,</hi> News came to <hi>Boſton,</hi> that the <hi>Indians</hi> had Burnt the Farm-houſe of Major <hi>Pinchon,</hi> ſcituate near <hi>Springfield,</hi> and killed much Cattel, and Burnt much Corn, which occaſioned his Son to abide ſtill in <hi>Boſton</hi> (he being before provided to go for <hi>London,</hi> with Capt. <hi>John Walley</hi> in the <hi>Johns Adventure,</hi> Mr. <hi>Pinchon's</hi> one Ship): It is judged that Major <hi>Pinchon's</hi> dammage may amount to eleven or twelve hundred Pound <hi>Ster<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</hi> This day alſo came the News to Mr. <hi>Purchas,</hi> that his Houſe and Goods were Burnt, his Wife and Children kill'd; the latter proved falſe: He was alſo bound in Capt. <hi>Walley</hi> for <hi>London,</hi> but remained at <hi>Boſton</hi> for ſome time, in order to the ſettling his Family there. His Loſs likewiſe amounted to above a thouſand Pound <hi>Sterling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the <hi>12th</hi> of <hi>October,</hi> a Body of <hi>Indians</hi> came to <hi>Springfield,</hi> who immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately fired the Town, and conſumed thirty two Houſes, and almoſt as many Barns, with their Corn and Hay.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Indians</hi> that did this Miſchief, were a company of thoſe ſort called <hi>Praying Indians,</hi> about forty in number, that alwayes dwelt near to <hi>Spring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field,</hi> and at that time were confined to their Town and a mile about it; but for their uſual Civility ſake, were permitted daily to have Converſe with the Town, about what Buſineſs they had, and at mid-night they did their Exploit. The Neighbouring Towns hearing it, and that it was done by them, Roſe without any Command or Leader, and ſlew all of them they could find, which was about thirty.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe tidings came this day from the <hi>Eaſtward,</hi> that they have killed twenty Men within this ten days; wherefore here is this <hi>20th</hi> of <hi>October,</hi> marched forty Men out of <hi>Boſton,</hi> for their Relief.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Narraganſets</hi> we fear more and more every day, will be perfidious to us, the time being paſt that they ſhould have delivered <hi>Squaw Sachem</hi> at <hi>Boston.</hi> Our Feares are the more encreaſed, as well in that we underſtand ſeveral of them appear up and down in Arms; however here is a Levie now coming out for a thouſand <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> to wait on them, which we hope may reduce them to good order, as well as recover <hi>Squaw Sachem</hi> out of their hands; which if ſhe be but taken by the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> her Lands will pay more then all the Charge we have been at in this unhappy War.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>October</hi> 28. This day by advice from <hi>Hatfield,</hi> we have this particular Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of what happened there.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Wedneſday,</hi> the <hi>19th</hi> of <hi>October,</hi> a party of <hi>Indians</hi> about ſeven Miles off <hi>Hatfield</hi> in the Woods, made ſeveral great Fires, to make the <hi>Engliſh</hi> think they were there, but as ſoon as ever they had ſet fire to the Wood, they came directly towards <hi>Hatfield,</hi> and about two Miles from <hi>Hatfield</hi> they lay in Buſhes by the way ſide undiſcoverable, thinking to cut off the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> in their way to the Fires: About Noon, they of <hi>Hatfield</hi> ſent ten Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men well armed, to Scout out and ſee what is the matter in the Woods; and in their way, the <hi>Indians</hi> at once ſhot down nine of the ten, and the other returned to <hi>Hatfield</hi> to carry the news: Capt. <hi>Samuel Moſeley</hi> being then not far from thence, with ſixty Men, was immediately ſent for, who preſently came. By four a Clock, there were come into the Town, above ſeven hundred <hi>Indians</hi> armed, and immediately ſet Fire in three places to the Town, but by care was ſoon quenched; Capt. <hi>Moſeley</hi> preſently engaged five hundred of theſe <hi>Indians,</hi> whilſt two hundred and more other <hi>Indians</hi>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:99949:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>were at the other end of the Town endeavouring to Fire it, There was alſo another Captain, with about ſixty Men not far off, who hearing the Guns, came immediately thither and ſet on the other Party of two hundred and odd; but two <hi>Engliſh</hi> Captains ſoon joyned together, and they had a Fight with thoſe ſeven hundred and odd <hi>Indians,</hi> for near two Hours time, till they could ſee no longer; in this Fight we loſt only three Men, and we judg we may have killed above an hundred <hi>Indians,</hi> we forced the reſt in great diſorder to run away, we forced them over a large River, who in their Swiming over, loſt all their Arms and Ammunition, and ſeveral were Drowned, as was ſeen the next day, This Fight doth much diſcourage them, and encourage our <hi>Engliſh:</hi> there were ten Men wounded of ours in the Fight, but none Mortally we hope.</p>
            <p>Care now is taken to ſatisfie the (reaſonable) deſires of the Commonal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, concerning Mr. <hi>Elliots Indians,</hi> and Capt. <hi>Guggins Indians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They that wear the name of <hi>Praying Indians,</hi> but rather (as Mr, <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah Uſhur</hi> termed <hi>Praying-Indians</hi>) they have made Preys of much <hi>Engliſh</hi> Blood, but now they are all reduced to their ſeveral Confinements; which is much to a general Satisfaction in that reſpect.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Dated from</hi> Boſton, <date>Novemb. 10. 1675.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have here encloſed you as large an Account as I can at preſent of the State of this Wilderneſs, in reſpect to the Heathens: I muſt confeſs, I was the willinger to take a little the more Pains in the Collecting thereof, for the ſakes of thoſe with you, who wiſh us well. Which if it may anſwer its intended end therein, the Labour in Writing will be well beſtowed. You may expect more from me as there is occaſion, mean vvhile I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
               <signed>Your Friend and Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 80.7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14.</p>
            </postscript>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:99949:11"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99949:11"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
